<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
<meta name="created" content="Mon May 11 14:47:50 EDT 2009"/>
<meta name="producer" content="Adobe Acrobat 9.0 Paper Capture Plug-in"/>
<meta name="Content-Type" content="application/pdf"/>
<title/>
</head>
<body>
<div class="page">
<p>AFWL- TR-7 4-49 AFWL- TR-
74-49 
CHEMP: A CODE FOR CALCULATION OF 
·HIGH-ALTITUDE EMP 
July 1974 
Final Report for Peri.6d March 1973 - December 1973 
.,' 
Approved for 'public release; distribution unlimited. 
AIR FORCE WEAPONS LABORATORY 
Air Force Systems Command 
Kirtland Air Force ~~8ZllL </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>AFWL-TR-74-49 
~ FORCE WEAPONS LABORATORY 
Air Force Systems Command 
Kirtland Air Force Base 
New Mexico 87117 
When US Government drawings, specifications, or other data are used for 
any purpose other than a definitely related Government procurement operation, 
the Government thereby incurs nO responsibility nor any obligation whatsoever, 
and the fact that the Government may have formulated, furnished, or in any way 
supplied the said drawings, specifications, or other data, is not to be 
regarded by implication or otherwise, as in any manner licensing the holder 
or any other person or corporation, or conveying any rights or permission to 
manufacture, use, or sell any patented invention that may in any way be 
related thereto. 
DO NOT RETURN THIS COPY. RETAIN OR DESTROY. 
;t </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>UNCLASS I FI ED A]),7f1~39 S'&gt;(,lIrity Cla&lt;;sificatinn 
DOCUMENT CONTROL DATA - R&amp; D -
(S('Cllrity (·111 ... .&lt;;;(;( l,tiofJ of fillo, Iwdy (If (Jhtdfltf t ,,,,,] ;tldf~xinl1"''''Q'/lti(l'' mil';' he entCrtHJ W"t~TI tI.,· '~vf:rlJlJ tnl'llf' ,., rlll"MItJ,,") 
, OF'(IGINA liNG A( TIVll Y ('orportlte nul/Jut) 2..:'. HLf&gt;()Pl ',r:C1JHt T,( CLA:'iSlf IC/. finN 
Air Force Heapons Laboratory (DYT) Unclassified 
Ki rt 1 and II.; r Force Base, New Mexico 87117 2h. G~OUP 
3 REP,?PT TITLE 
CHEt~P : A CODE FOR CALCULATION OF HIGH-ALTITUDE EMP 
4. DESCR""TIVE NOTES (Type of report and inclusive dates) 
Final Reoort for Period March 1973 - December 1973 
5. AU THOR(S) (First name, middle initial, last name) 
Leon A. l~i ttwer, Capt, USAF; Gregory H. Canavan, t1aj, USAF; James E. Brau, Capt, USAF 
6. REPORT DATE 7a. TOTAL NO. OFPAGES if rb. NO. 0; REFS July 1974 .~ ....... 0&lt; 
8a. CONTRACT OR GRANT NO. 9a. ORIGINATOR'S REPORT NUMBERIS) 
b. PROJECT NO. 8809 AFWL-TR-74-49 
c. Task 18 9b. OTHER REPORT NOIS) (Any other numbers that may be assigned 
this report) 
d. 
10. DISTRIBUTION STATEMENT 
Approved for public release; distribution un 1 imited. 
11. SUPPLEMENTARY NOTES 12. SPONSORING MILITARY ACTIVITY 
AFWL (DYT) 
Kirtland AFB, NM 87117 
13. ABSTRACT (Distribution L imitati on Statement A) 
\ 
CHEMP is a code originally designed to examine the effects of self-consistency on 
high-altitude fields by using a particle pushing model for the current calculation 
and the high-frequency approximation for calculating the fields. CHEMP has been 
extended to study the effects of nonforward Compton scattering, varying gamma 
energies, and elastic nuclear scattering. 
'. 
_.---
---- -
Reproduced by 
" NATIONAL TECHNICAL 
INFORMATION SERVICE 
U S Department of Commerce 
Springfield VA 22151 
I UNCLASSIFIED 
Security Classification </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>14. 
UNCLASSIFIED 
Security Classification 
KEY WORDS 
..... 
Hi gh-altitude Er1P 
Electromagnetic pulse (EMP) 
~~/ 
, eL 
I 
LINK A LINK B LIN K C 
ROLE WT ROLE WT ROLE 'liT 
:-
I 
i 
UNCLASSIFIED 
Security Classification </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>AFWL-TR-74-49 
CHEMP: A CODE FOR CALCULATION OF HIGH-ALTITUDE EMP 
Leon A. Wittwer 
Capt USAF 
Gregory H. Canavan 
Maj USAF 
James E. Brau 
Capt USAF 
Final Report for Period March 1973 - December 1973 
Approved for public release; distribution unlimited. </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>AFWL-TR-74-49 
FOREWORD 
This research was performed under Program Element 62601F, Project 8809, 
Task 18. 
Inclusive dates of research were March 1973 through December 1973. The 
report was submitted 22 March 1974 by the Ai r Force ~Jeapons Laboratory Project 
Officer, Captain Leon A. Wittwer (DYT). The former project officer was Captain 
James E. Brau. 
This technical report has been reviewed and is apprOved. 
La~1J~ 
LEON A. WITTWER 
Captain, USAF 
Project Officer 
)J;.u ",tl /J /I'l~--
JAY R. ROLAND 
r~aj or, USAF 
Chief, Theoretical Physics Branch 
ii 
DAVID M ERICSON, JR. 
Lt Colonel, USAF 
Chief, Technology Divison </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>AFWL-TR-74-49 
ABSTRACT 
(Distribution Limitation Statement A) 
CHEMP is a code originally designed to examine the effects of self-consistency 
on high-altitude fields by using a partic']e pushing model for the current calcu 
lation and the high-frequency approximation for calculating the fields. CHEMP 
has been extended to study the effects of nonforward Compton scattering, varying 
gamma energies, and elastic nuclear scattering. 
iii/iv </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>AFWL-TR-74-49 
CONTENTS 
Section Page 
I INTRODUCTION 1 
I! GENERAL ALGORITHM 2 
II! CURRENT SOURCE 8 
IV ENERGY CALCULATIONS 11 
APPENDIXES 
I Physical Constants 13 
II Numerical Methods 15 
REFERENCES 16 
v/vi </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>AFWL-TR-74-49 
SECTION I 
INTRODUCTION 
The purpose of this report is to describe the CHEMP code and its usage. 
CHEMP was originally developed to examine the effects of self-consistency in 
high-altitude EMP calculations. The code then went through continual develop 
ment to look at other topics of interest. The present version described here 
is state of the art in all aspects of the physical model and can perform calcu 
lations for all the known high-altitude EMP scenarios. This paper is in four 
sections. The first is a general description of the algorithm. Subsequent 
sections deal with specific portions of the methodology in greater detail. 
1 </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>AF~JL-TR-74-49 
SECTION II 
GENERAL ALGORITHM 
CHEMP is based on a particle pushing model for the Compton electron dynamics 
and the high-frequency approximation (ref. 1) for the electromagnetic fields. 
The fundamental equations are those for the motion of the particles and those 
which determine the fields. For the particle's motion in retarded time 
(1) 
(2) 
where vk in the velocity of the kth particle, y equals (1 - IVkI2/c2)-1/2, ~r is 
a unit vector along the line of sight from the burst, T is retarded time, and 
dWk/dx is the energy loss per unit path length from ionization (appendix II). 
For the fields in retarded time 
where ET, BT, and JT are the transverse electric field, magnetic field, and 
current, and Er,Br and J r are the radial electric field, magnetic field, and 
current. The currents include the conduction currents. 
The fundamental equations are all expressed in retarded time 
T = t - ric 
2 
(3) 
(4) 
(5 ) 
(6 ) </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>AFWL-TR-74-49 
where T is retarded time, t is absolute time, and r is the coordinate along Q,r' 
The transform of the equation of motion (1) is seen by differentiating (6) to 
give 
(7) 
For the field transform the time derivative in (7) is, at constant r 
aT/a t :: 1 (8) 
(9) 
where (9) is the transform of the gradient operator. 
The transform of the charge density is derived from (9) and the invariance 
of the form of the charge continuity equation as 
(10) 
The retarded charge density at r can be expressed as a sum over all particles 
at r in the form 
(11 ) 
where 6T in the proper time volume element and WT'(rk,Tk) is the production rate 
of Compton electrons per unit volume per retarded time at (rk,Tk) where the kth 
particle at (r,T) orginated and ;s given by 
where N is the total number of gammas that scatter the type of electron of y 
(12) 
interest, N is the particle density at rk, 0KN is the appropriate cross section 
3 </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>AFWL-TR-74-49 
for Compton scattering (appendix I), and f(Tk) is the retarded time dependence 
of the gamma source and is normalized to one. 
From equation (10) for the kth electron 
(13) 
Thus 
(14 ) 
and 
(15 ) 
All of the quantities in equation (1) through (4) have been accounted for 
except for the conduction portion of the current. The conduction current is 
expressed as 
(16 ) 
where &lt; V &gt; is the drift velocity of the conduction electrons. The properties 
of the conduction electron, the drift velocity, density, and mean energy are 
calculated with the following swarm (ref. 2) equations 
d&lt; V &gt; ef &lt; V &gt; dne 
dt = m- - vm &lt; V &gt; - ne ~ (17) 
d&lt; U &gt; eE • &lt; V&gt; - v « U &gt; - U ) + S = dt u 0 
(18 ) 
&lt; U &gt; dne 
ne dt 
4 </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>AFWL-TR-74-49 
(19 ) 
wl~ere vm' vu' YT' Ye are the momentum exchange co 11 is i on frequency, energy 
exchange collision frequency, Townsend air breakdown coefficient, and electron 
recombination coefficient. All are functions of the particle density and mean 
energy &lt; U &gt; (see appendix I). Uo is the ambient thermal energy. S is an energy 
source term which includes energy lost due to recombination and air breakdown 
and that gained from ionization by primary Compton electrons. Ee is the energy 
lost per primary ionization event by the Compton electrons (appendix I). Subse 
quent ionization by secondary electrons can be handled by an appropriate ioniza 
tion lag model. Ns represents the source of later ionization from the secondaries. 
This completes the discussion of the fundamental equation used. The remainder 
of this section will examine the structure of the numerical algorithm used in 
solving the relevant equation on a space-retarded time grid. 
r· I 1- r· 1 
The quantities E, J, and B are known at (i-1, j-l), (i-l, j), and (i, j-l). 
In addition ne , &lt; V&gt;, &lt; U &gt;, and vk for all particles created before Tj - 1 are 
known at (i, j-l). It;s assumed that a particle created at r i always is close 
enough so that it can be assumed to be at ri . First the appropriate quantities 
are initialized at (i, j), i.e., 
5 </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>AHJL- TR-74-49 
E~ = E~ 1 1-1 
B~ = B~ 1 1-1 
&lt; U &gt;~ = &lt; U j &gt;. 1 1 1-
&lt; V &gt;~ &lt; - j = V &gt;. 1 1 1-
and the necessary particles are created at (i, j-l). The weight of new particles 
created at (i, j-l) is 
Weight = N Ny 0KN exp (-of
ri 
where np is the number of particles created. If np is one, generally the parti 
cle has the average scatter energy and is directed forward. The option also 
exists to create seve'ral particles at a point to simulate the Compton electron 
distribution. This will be discussed in greater detail in the source section. 
Now 
where k includes the newly created particles. Let Be be the earth's magnetic 
field. The basic iteration loop proceeds as follows. 
1. Update v~ for all k by solving equation (1). The solution, obtained 
iteratively, is time centered in all terms including those nonlinear in the 
velocity. The total magnetic field is that from the particles plus Be' A one 
percent convergence criteria in Ivll is used. If desired, the MRC obliquity 
factor (ref. 3) can be used in this step. 
2. Calculate the contribution to J~ from the Compton electron by using 1 • 
equation (15), using the appropriate weight and the just calculated v~'s. 
6 </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>AFWL-TR-74-49 
3. Update nj and &lt; U &gt;~ by solving equations (18) and (19) iteratively. 
ei ' 
The solutions are time centered in all quantities, and a one-percent convergence 
criteria is used on &lt; U &gt;~. , 
4. Update &lt; V&gt;j by solving equation (17) where all quantities are time 
centered, using the new data calculated in step 3. 
5. Sum the conduction and Compton currents for J1 
6. Update E~ and B~ by using equations (3), (4), and (5) where again 
all quantities are centered. 
7. Test the magnitude of the new f~ against the old. If the variation 
is less than one percent, the cell solution is complete. If not, return to step 
1 and continue with the updated quantities until convergence is reached. 
The above procedure is used to solve for all time the space cells in the 
grid. The algorithm calculates for all time at a particular space point before 
proceeding on to the next space point. This procedure is the most efficient. 
This completes the general description of the algorithm. 
7 </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>AFVJL-TR-74-49 
SECTION III 
CURRENT SOURCE 
The current source package defines the location, time, energy, and direction 
of all the Compton particles at creation. Only primary Compton events are con 
sidered. There are several options available in CHEMP. The simplest option, 
used primarily when absolute field strengths are unimportant, is producing one 
particle each time step with the average Compton scattering energy and directed 
forward. The gamma spectrum is monoenergetic. If 0 KN is the total Compton 
cross section and Os is the Compton scattering cross section, then the average 
Compton electron energy ;s 
E = (1- l)hV 0 KN 
where hv ;s the gamma energy. The weight of each particle created is determined 
/ by the y curve and the attenuation in the atmosphere 
y = N f(T) y 
where Ny is the total number of gammas. f(T) is the time dependence of the 
gamma source and is normalized to one. The gamma flux at Rand T is 
The deposition rate per unit time and volume is 
8 </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>AFWL-TR-74-49 
and the weight of a particle is just the rate integrated over the differential 
time element. 
T+6T 
Weight = f R dT 
T 
The next option is generally used for most problems. The gamma spectrum is still 
monoenergetic, but now several particles are created at each point in time and 
space. The directions and energies of the particles are created to simulate the 
initial Compton scattering distribution. As a typical example, to simulate the 
distribution from a 1.5 MeV source, sixteen particles are created at each point 
in space and time. Four polar scattering angles, 0.146, 0.357, 0.624, and 1.04 
radians and four azimuthal angles, 0, TI/29 TI, and 3TI/2 are used to specify the 
direction of the particles. These angles were chosen so that all particles have 
equal weights. The particle energies are now a function of the polar scattering 
angle. Let 8e be the electron scattering angle. Then 
where 
The weight of a particle is 
Weight = (1/16) 
a = hv/m c2 o 
9 </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>AFWL-TR-74-49 
Other weighting schemes with different polar scattering angles are occa 
sionally used to test the accuracy of these sources. The last major option is 
whether or not to use a gamma spectrum with either of the above two options. 
To implement an energy spectrum, the above desired option is done for each 
energy in the gamma energy spectrum. It is presently assumed that one f(T) 
function describes all gamma energies. 
Other variations on this source package are available with minimal changes. 
10 </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>AFWL-TR-74-49 
SECTION IV 
ENERGY CALCULATIONS 
The CHEMP code was originally built to study the energetics of high-altitude 
EMP. Six energy totals are kept for every calculation. The first is the total 
Compton energy deposited over all time and from r = 0 to R. For a monoenergetic 
spectrum 
where E is the energy of the Compton electrons and WT'(r,T) is the source func 
tion define in section II 
The second energy term is the energy dissipated via the conduction electrons, 
gi yen by 
where n(r,T) is the free electron density and (V) is the drift velocity. 
The third term is the radiated energy that has propagated by the spatial 
point r. 
where c is the velocity of light and ET ;s the transverse field. 
The next energy sum is the longitudinal field energy, given by 
R 
We = f /fe(r,Tmax ) /2r2dr 
o 
11 </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>AFHL-TR-74-49 
where Ee is the longitudinal field. The kinetic energy remaining in the Compton 
electrons at Tmax from R = a to R is found by performing the appropriate sum to 
get Wk' 
The last energy is that lost by the Compton electrons in ionizing collisions. 
This term, Wi' is also summed as the calculation progresses. If the calculations 
were exact, then 
W. + Wd + W + H 1 e r 
In general, the error in total energy in CHEt~P is less than one-half percent. 
12 </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>AHJL~TR-74-49 
1. ENERGY LOSS EQUATION 
APPENDIX I 
PHYSICAL CONSTANTS 
The energy loss equation (ref. 3) used in CHEMP is 
where NZ is the total electron density, B = vIc, y = (l - B2)-1/2, and I is 
taken as 86 eV. 
2. COMPTON CROSS SECTION 
0 KN = 2rrr021 (l+a) [2{1+a)/{1+2a) - ln {1+2a)/a] /a2. 
+ In{1+2a)/2 - {1+3a)/{1+2a)2~ 
a = hv/m c2 o 
hv = photon energy 
3. AIR BREAKDOWN COEFFICIENT, MOMENTUM EXCHANGE COLLISION FREQUENCY, AND ENERGY 
EXCHANGE COLLISION FREQUENCY 
For a given characteristic electron energy 
13 </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>AFWL-TR-74-49 
"energy = N (1.3X10-11 (1+4.4x104 (5)0.32/(1+ 1.93x103 (10)0.138 
+ 4.13x1010 £5.22/( (1+0.06£7)0.456(1+1.68x10-3 (4)0.097)) 
v = 1 25xl0-7 NEO.935 (1+0.093 E1.5)0.405 /(1+1.26 El •67 )0.373 
momentum . \ 
Where N is the particle density. There fits are variations of fits used by 
Higgins, Longmire, and OIDell (ref. 2). 
4. ENERGY LOST PER PRIMARY IONIZATION 
is 
For a Compton electron of energy E eV the average energy lost per ionizaton 
E &gt; 250 Kev 
250 KeV &gt; E &gt; 0.640 Kev 
0.640 KeV &gt; E 
Ee = 86 eV 
Ee = 7.705 In(E) - 9.79 
Ee = 1.8 In(E) + 28.4 
5. ELECTRON RECOMBINATION COEFFICIENT 
Three body recombination 
Ye = 2.78xlO-
31 N2/(1+12.5 E) 
3 
Two body dissociative recombination 
Y
e 
= 4.85xlO-12 N/(1+3.45 E-4.8),.29 
2 
Total recombination 
14 </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>AFWL-TR-74-49 
APPENDIX II 
NUMERICAL METHODS 
The general form of the first order differential equations solved is 
af 
ax 
Two numerical forms are used in finding the solution. The first is 
The second is 
where 
f i -1/ 2 = (fi + fi_1)/2 
xi-1/2 = (xi + xi-1)/2 
Yi-1/2 = (Yi + Yi-1)/2 
(20) 
(21) 
(22) 
Both of the above equations are solved iteratively. These forms are used 
primarily because they are two point schemes. Thus, the increment, 6x, can be 
charged without incurring any loss of accuracy due to loss of centering. Also 
the implicit nature of the solution ensures a high degree of numerical stability. 
The error in equation (21) is ~ (6x)3f' I '(€)/12 
The error in equation (22) is also of the same order. 
15 </p>
</div>
<div class="page">
<p>. i
AFWL-TR-74-49 
REFERENCES 
1. Karzas, W. J. and Latter, R., Detection of the Electromagnetic Radiation 
from Nuclear Explosions in Space, RAND Corporation, RM-4306, 1964. 
2. Higgins, D. F., Longmire, C. L., O'Dell, A. A., A Method for Estimating the 
X-ray Produced Electromagnetic Pulse Observed in the Source Re~;on of a 
High-Altitude Burst, Mission Research Corporation, MRC-R-54, , 73. 
3. Evans, R. 0., The Atomic Nucleus, McGraw-Hill Book Company, New York, 1969 . 
16 </p>
</div>
